Someone's coming!
来た
There's a cliff up ahead. If we keep going like this, it'll be dangerous.
この先　崖でしたよ
このまま進んでたら　ヤバかったっすよ
ガードレールの内側　行きましょう
Let's stay inside the guard rails.
Ow!
痛っ！
20 years after the date of my birth, I came face to face with true darkness for the first time.
生まれて２０と幾年　初めて
真の闇というものと対面した
No worries, no worries.
大丈夫　大丈夫
Dear viewers, might you be aware
視聴者諸君は　ミツバチが
大量失踪しているという話を　ご存じだろうか？
that large numbers of honeybees are said to be disappearing?
何故　わたしが夜の山奥で　オリエンテーリングの
ようなことを　繰り広げているかというと
Why do I ask?
Because this nighttime orienteering deep in the mountains unfolding before you
is due to my own disappearance as a worker bee.
わたしもまた　失踪した働き蜂だからである
O-O-Ozu...
「こっちのみずは　あーまいぞ…」
The water over here tastes lovely...
The water over there tastes bad...
What the hell have you done?
お前は　いったい　何をしでかしたのだ！
Heh heh, nothing at all.
ゲヘッ　何でもないですよ
Let's walk to the next train stop.
一駅　歩きましょう　その方が　よさそうですね
I think that'll be for the best.
This is truly hell, and it's all that honey's...
全ては　蜂みつが
or rather, it's all because of my total infatuation.
いや　まったく
ほれたら地獄とは
まさに　このことである
Who is responsible?
責任者は　誰か？
おそらく　わたしであろう　今回ばかりは
Probably me.
Just this time...
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
on a stretched out window
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
Then they hide themselves away
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
so that they can be covered up
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
I will meet you someday
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
ikou
行こう
Going
Then I was a freshman university student
当時　ピカピカの大学１回生だった
わたしの目の前には
and before me lay open countless doors to that rose-colored campus life.
ばら色のキャンパスライフへの
扉が無数に開かれていた
"Softball Circle Honwaka"
"Recruiting"
It seems that Honwaka reserves a corner of the sports field each week and plays softball,
「ほんわか」とは　週末に　グラウンドの隅を借りて
ソフトボールをやっているサークルらしく
時折　行われる試合にだけ参加
with the occasional game thrown in.
あとは　自由ということである
Other than that it's totally free.
ソフトボールサークルと　銘打っているものの
The logo might say "softball circle,"
but it looks like their main purpose is to engage in warm-hearted intermingling.
ほんのり温かく交流することが　主眼らしい
ここなら　連日連夜　白球を追い回して
Here there is no practicing day and night chasing around white balls.
汗と涙と根性を丸出しにし
There is no sweat, no tears, no guts.
全国大会を　目指すようなこともあるまい
No one is aiming for any national tournament...
うつうつたる高校生活よ　さらば
Farewell, my melancholic high school days.
こういう集いに加わって　さわやかに汗を流しながら
友達１００人つくるのも悪くない
It would not be so bad to join with this bunch,
and while breaking into an invigorating sweat, make a hundred friends!
修業を積んだ暁には
美女たちと言葉のキャッチボールをこなす
I will surely master cordial conversation
while playing catch with beautiful women during early morning practice.
社交性が身に付くに違いない
It is an ability that I must master to make my mark on this world.
これは　社会に出ていくためにも
ぜひとも　身に付けておかなければならない能力だ
It is most definitely not simply because I wish to converse with pretty girls.
決して　美女と交流したいわけではない
技術を身に付けたいのだ
I want to learn the art!
But if, after mastering the art,
しかし　技術を身に付けた結果　美女も　ついてくるなら
a beautiful woman wished to come with me, I would have no reason to decline.
特に　それを拒む理由はない
はい　これ
No worries...
大丈夫さ
Fear not, and come to me!
安心して　僕のところにおいで～！
"Softball Circle Honwaka"
Unfortunately I was an idiot beyond all redemption.
しかし　わたしは
手の施しようのない　アホだったのである
Now, please listen carefully to the circumstances which befell me.
これから　じっくり　事の　てん末を　お聞かせしたい
途中退席は　認めない
And I will accept no leaving in the middle of this!
The softball circle Honwaka was just as the name says.
ソフトボールサークル　ほんわかは　その名が示すとおり
春がすみの　かかった空に浮かぶ
雲のように　ほんわかとしていた
Like the covering clouds of a springtime haze, warm and snuggly.
The thing that interested me the most was their male/female ratio.
その中でも　気に入ったのが　男女比の案配であった
Please, eat!
召し上がってください
It's an organic sandwich and tea with royal jelly.
有機野菜のサンドイッチと　ロイヤルゼリーの　お茶です
It's most definitely not that I judge everything primarily by such a criterion,
わたしは　決して　物事の判断において
そのことを　重点的に　気にしているわけではないが
いかにも　これは　異性間の進行が
はぐくめそうな　絶妙な比率ではないか
but was not this the best possible ratio to nurture intimacy with the opposite sex?
ただ　一つ気になったのは
The only thing that worried me...
...was that it was a bit too "warm and snuggly."
ほんわかし過ぎている　ということだった
To put it simply, everyone was far too nice.
ひと言でいうと　皆　善人過ぎる
That place doesn't use much pesticide, but the prices are quite reasonable, don't you think?
あそこは　低農薬なのに
リーズナブルに提供してるよね
The idea of getting ducks to eat harmful insects is quite effective.
カモに害虫を食べさせるっていう
アイデアが効いているんだよ
The consumer shouldn't have to suffer just because something
生産者の都合で　消費者が
被害をかぶってるのは　おかしいよ
せめて　選択肢がないと
is more convenient for the producer.
国民に　お金を与えないようにして
選択の余地を奪っているんだよ
People should at least have options.
They take away the people's choice because they don't want them to get money.
でも　たま～に　カップ麺を食べたくなるよね
But sometimes you feel like a cup ramen, you know?
体に悪そうな脂っこいやつとかさ
You know, the ones that are bad for you with lots of oil...
I think adults have to set a proper example.
大人が　ちゃんと　見本を見せてあげることが
教育なんだと思うよ
If we can show the right attitude to the children, then our children will grow up normal.
子供に　正しい大人の態度を見せてれば
変な子は　育たないと思う
They say that children who are loved properly from a young age don't go astray.
小さいころに　ちゃんと　愛情をもらった子供は
We could cross the street on a red light,
ぐれないっていうし　赤信号でも渡ってみせて
法律を　うのみにしないリテラシーを
教えてやればいいんだよね
to teach them the concept of not blindly accepting the law without question.
Before long I was no longer part of the conversation,
いつまでたっても　会話の中に入れない
and every time I uttered a word
わたしが　何か発言するたびに
皆　優しい笑顔を顔に　はり付けたまま
everyone would fall silent with kind smiles still plastered on their faces.
黙りこんでしまうのだった
常に　にこにこ　微笑み　口論もせず　わい談もしない
Among those constantly brightly smiling faces, with no dissent or dirty talk,
唯一　親近感を持ったのは
妖怪のような顔をした　小津という男であった
was a single man I felt close to named Ozu with a face like a youkai.
独特の話術で
With his peculiar conversational skills he managed to secure his place within the circle,
サークル内での一定の位置を
確保することに　成功してはいたが
but he seemed to have trouble smiling and laughing innocently.
にこにこと　天真らんまんに　ほほ笑むことに
困難を感じているらしく…
That's quite amusing.
イヒヒッ　それは面白いですな
Giving the impression of an evil that could not be hidden lurking inside his gut,
その腹の中に潜む邪悪さを　隠しようもないという印象で
笑うという筋肉を　そもそも
持って生まれてきていないような不自然な笑い方である
he had a laugh so unnatural it was like he wasn't born with the proper muscles to do it.
They say a drowning man will even gasp at straw,
溺れる者　わらをも　つかむというが
わたしは　すぐに
この　ぬらりひょんのような男と意気投合した
so I immediately hit it off with such a slippery fellow.
It's okay, it's not your fault.
いいよ　いいよ　君が悪いんじゃない
悪いとすれば　こういう状況を
つくり出した　僕ら　みんなが悪いんだ
It's everyone's fault for creating such a situation.
Who could learn the art of pleasant sociability through such lukewarm interaction?
こうした　ぬるい交流を通して　わたしが
平凡な社会性を身に付けたか　といえば　そうはいかぬ
わたしの堪忍袋は　パツンパツンに張り詰め
My patience had almost worn through.
キューバ危機に匹敵する　一触即発の状態にあった
It was a situation that could explode at any time, like the Cuban Missile Crisis.
しかし　そんなギリギリいっぱいのわたしが
１回生の　ある夏の日
However, while I remained on the brink one day in the summer of my freshman year,
ほんわかと　心が　ひもとけてしまいそうな
運命の出会いを果たした
I had a fateful encounter which melted my heart in a warm embrace.
Her beauty was incredible.
彼女の美しさは　圧倒的であった
I felt like her "whoa" factor was of 100% purity,
純度１００％のふわふわしたものでできていると思われ
like if you tried to speak with her she'd be too bright to look at directly.
話し掛けようにも　あまりに　まぶしく
まともに見ることすら　かなわなかった
It seemed she was an important member of Honwaka,
彼女は　ほんわかの　重要なメンバーであるらしく
and she was surrounded by people,
smiling as she listened to their conversation.
彼女を取り巻く人々の話を　にこやかに聞いていた
国家試験に受かりました　ロイヤルゼリーの　おかげです
I passed the state exam thanks to the royal jelly!
集中シールで　成績が上がりました
My grades rose thanks to those concentration patches!
It's all thanks to Honwaka that I've come this far.
これぐらいで助かってるのはほんわかの　おかげです
She was the personification of the raven-haired maiden I pictured in my mind.
彼女は　わたしが思い描いた　黒髪の乙女そのものであった
If I walked with her along the mall of Sanjoukawara or something,
彼女と　三条河原町のアーケードなんぞ歩けたら
道行く誰もがうらやむような
さわやかな２人になるであろうことは　間違いなかった
I bet people would surely be jealous looking at the fresh young couple walking down the road.
Oh, look at you. Should you be eating something so unhealthy?
おやおや　そんな　体に　悪い物　食べてていいんですか？
Shut up!
うるさい！
Neko Ramen is a mysterious food cart that only appears around Tadasu Forest.
猫ラーメンは　糺の森かいわいに出没する　謎の屋台である
猫から　だしを取っているという噂であるが　定かでない
It's rumored they use actual cats to make the broth, but there's no proof of it.
The owner says it started living nearby after he began feeding it used bonito flakes,
マスターの話では　出がらしの
かつお節を　あげているうちに
すみ着くようになったと言うが
警察に通報されれば
but if he was ever reported to the police I'm sure his cart would be shut down.
一発で営業停止処分であろう
しかし　その味は　無類である
However, the taste is unmatched.
Kohinata-san is a freshman like us.
われわれと同じ　１回生ですよ　小日向さんは
Don't underestimate me,
I can tell what you're thinking at least.
見くびらないでください　あなたが
何　考えてるかくらい　分かりますよ
I hear she's the only daughter of the health food company
彼女は　ほんわかの母体である
健康食品会社の一人娘らしいです
that's the umbrella group for Honwaka.
The softball circle Honwaka is a branch of the health food company Honwaka,
ソフトボールサークル　ほんわかは
健康食品会社ほんわかの　下部組織
and she is the company's poster-child.
そして　彼女は　そこの広告塔なんです
Despite that, she doesn't have much enthusiasm for PR work, and only appears once in a while.
とはいえ　それほど広報活動には　熱心じゃないようで
たまにしか出てこない
Now that I think about it, I've never seen her play softball.
というか　ソフトボールしてるのは見たことないです
She may have shown up today.
今日は　たまたま　出てきたらしいのですが
But if you want to see her regularly,
おーっ　彼女と普通に会うには
それ相応の立場にならないと　難しいらしいです
it seems like you need to raise your position to a more suitable level.
At Honwaka, your rank in the circle rises the more you buy their products.
ほんわかでは　そこの製品を　大量に買えば買うほど
サークル会員としてのランクが　上がっていくという
ランクが上がれば　上位会員のみ　懇親会に出席でき
With a high rank you can attend meetings only for high-ranked members,
彼女に会える確率も　高くなるらしい
and that seemed like it'd raise my chances of meeting her.
Well, if you want to run along the path of love, I can't stop you.
まあ　それでも　あなたが　恋路に走るというのなら
わたしは止めませんが
Idiot. Who would go buying health food products like that?
アホめ　誰が　そんな理由で　健康食品など
Isn't that like saying she's some grand prize you can win if you collect enough box tops?
それでは　まるで彼女が
応募切符を集めて当たる懸賞品ではないか！
Here you go, 30 portions of supplements and health drinks.
はい　サプリメントと　ドリンク３０食ずつね
すごい頑張ってるね
You're really working hard!
Royal jelly is produced by the worker bees after ingesting pollen they've collected.
ロイヤルゼリーは　ミツバチが集めてきた花粉を
働き蜂が　体内に入れて生成したものだ
希少であるため　生産コストは　ぐんと跳ね上がる
Its rarity causes the production cost to skyrocket.
When I first heard the cost I thought it was a scam,
最初に値段を聞いたときは　詐欺じゃないかと思ったが
製法を聞くと　どうやら　インチキではないらしく
but when I heard how it was made
I realized it wasn't some fraud,
値段も　他社のものと比べても　それなりに妥当であった
and comparing the price with other companies seemed about right.
The only problem was that my own economic situation became somewhat unbalanced.
問題は　わたしの経済事情と　少々　釣り合わないことで
それまで　たっぷりと取っていた　睡眠時間を削って
All the time I had to sleep disappeared, and I had to work day and night.
夜も昼もなく　働かねばならなかった
Even if it's high quality stuff, just eating it all at once will,
高級食品といえど　これだけ一気食いしては
on the contrary, be bad for you.
むしろ　体に良くないであろう
If you take a lot, then any more than the set portion won't be absorbed,
たくさん取ってもある　一定量以上は
吸収されずに流れ出てしまうと
and the rest will just wash out of your system, or so I heard.
どこかで聞いたことがある
Thinking about that, I was afraid of going to the bathroom,
そう考えると　かわやへ行くのも　はばかれる
さぞや　栄養のある落とし物であろう
for it was sure to leave behind precious nutrition.
I bet you got sick because you didn't take these!
きっと　これ食べてなかったら　病気になってるよ
送ってあげたら　おじいさんの病気が治ったの
My grandpa's illness got better when I gave them to him!
Thanks to the health food, my lifestyle got more and more unhealthy.
健康食品のおかげで　わたしの生活態度は
どんどん不健康になっていった
それでも健康なのは
Although it's thought that healthy food leads to good health,
健康食品のおかげであるとも　思われたが
perhaps I would have been just as healthy if I had done nothing but sleep.
何もせず　寝て過ごしても
同じく　健康だったかもしれなかった
"Popper Certificate"
"Stepper Certificate"
"Jumper Certificate"
"Winner Certificate"
"Wholer Certificate"
"Plighter Certificate"
"Bee Missionary"
Healthy honey!
健康蜂みつ
体に　いい蜂みつあめ～
Honey candy for your health!
Don't be surprised, but two years had passed.
驚くなかれ　それから２年の歳月が流れた
And I hadn't seen her even once since that day.
彼女には　あの日以来　一度も　お目にかかれていない
I wanted to obtain happiness quickly more than health, the environment, or world order...
わたしは　健康や環境問題　世界の秩序より
個人的な幸せを　速やかに手に入れたかった
この２年間の不毛さは何か？
How incredibly wasted were these past two years.
大金を　あくせく稼ぎ出し
There's no looking back on the incredible amount of money I earned and then spent.
惜しみなく　つぎ込んだものから　見返りがない
健康になりましょう！
Let's be healthy!
Confirm with the barcode.
バーコードで確認を
If the page is deleted, then it's an attack from someone.
もし　そのページが削除されたときは
何者かによる攻撃です
This honey candy will protect you from the flu!
インフルエンザに負けない　蜂みつあめ！
ＮＡＳＡの科学者が発見した　というものなんです
It's something that was discovered by NASA.
We were told not to tell anyone before it was announced, but...
発表前なので　いけないと　言われてるんですけど…
いや　ネットの書き込みを　信用しては　いけませんよ
No, you mustn't believe everything you read on the Internet.
I'd like to inform my dear viewers: this is definitely not my style.
視聴者諸君だけには　断っておきたいが
こうしたことは　特に　わたしの主義ではない
信ぴょう性があるかと　問われれば
And if you question my credibility,
there's nothing to look into and I have no answer.
調べたことがないので　特に答えようもない
いらないよ
I don't want any.
Let's do our best.
頑張りましょう
Finally, the strain of these two years caused me to snap.
ついに　２年間　張り詰めきった
わたしの堪忍袋の緒が切れた
They say tourists walking down Shinyougoku could hear that business was booming.
その景気の良い音は
新京極を歩く観光客にまで　聞こえたという
Trying to run from people's prying eyes,
before I knew it I had come to Kiyamachi.
人々の好奇の目から　逃れるようにして
気が付くと　わたしは　木屋町に来ていた
And there an old fortune teller was emitting an eerie aura.
そこでは　占いの老婆が
ただならぬ妖気を　垂れ流していたが
どうせ　身のある助言など　もらえないであろう
I was sure she wouldn't give me any concrete advice, though.
あなたは　不満を　抱いてらっしゃるようじゃな
You are wrapped in unease, are you not?
ちょっと待ってください！　わたしは　別に相談など！
Hold it! I didn't ask for a consultation or anything.
I can sense you have much talent.
あなたは　大変　才能も　おありのようじゃし
老婆の慧眼に脱帽した
I took off my helmet to the old woman's keen insight.
You could tell it was me?
この姿でも分かりますか？
Anyway, I feel there's an opportunity you can't let pass by.
とにかく　好機を　逃さないことが肝心じゃ
好機？
Opportunity?
あなたの目の前に　ぶら下がってる好機を
つかまえてごらんなさい
Grab the opportunity that is dangling right in front of you.
はい　５，０００円　えっ？
That'll be 5,000 yen!
そんなとき　待ちに待った　全国会合への誘いが届いた
And then...
I received any invitation to the national assembly I'd been waiting and waiting for!
The national assembly is said to be a two day, two night ceremony
全国会合は　山奥にある　ほんわかの本部で
２泊３日の合宿形式で　行われるという
deep in the mountains at Honwaka's headquarters.
Now, please remove your blindfolds.
では　目隠しを取ってください
The is the nucleus of Honwaka,
こちらが　様々な　最新技術開発に成功し
built with the latest technology and techniques,
今や　企業スパイからも　狙われている
which is being targeted by spies even now.
ほんわかの中枢部です
Please take all care to keep what you see and hear to yourself.
くれぐれも　見聞きしたものは　ご内密に
We left our luggage in our rooms and headed to tour the factory.
われわれは　部屋に荷物を置いて工場の見学へと向かった
The place where we make the candy does not use any machinery.
生あめを作るところは　機械では　できないんです
全て手作業で　無添加　１００％の手作り
Everything is 100% done by hand, with no additives of any sort.
やはり　本当にいいものは　人の力でないと
To create something wonderful, it must be done by hand, yes?
It doesn't look like 100% to me...
１００％じゃないようですが
Less than 1%.
１％以下ですよ
It was then that a flag about 3 tatami in size emblazoned with "Danger!" was unfurled within me.
そのとき　何かが　わたしの中で　危ないと書かれた
畳　３畳分はあろうかという
旗を振っていた
After that we had a perfunctory friendly softball game
この後　申し訳程度に　ソフトボールの親善試合をし
有機農場や養蜂場を　見て回った
and then went around the organic farm and beehives.
There are those that try to stop us for their own crooked profits.
曲がったことで
私腹を肥やしてる　人間からすると
わたしたちは邪魔者ですよ
でも　負けたらいかんと　思いますね
But I don't think we can lose.
やっぱり　正しいものだけが　最後に祝福を受けるんです
I believe that the righteous will be blessed in the end.
これ　ホント
I mean, really.
You all did great getting here.
君たちは　よく頑張って　ここまで来ました
I bet you all got some funny looks.
変な目で見られたでしょう？
おでこに　シール　はったりして
Like when you had patches stuck on your forehead.
But it's odd because it works!
でも　それが効くんだから　不思議だよね
疑う人は味わえない　超自然のパワー
The unbelievers can't taste the amazing power of nature!
You all have found salvation.
皆さんは解脱できました
でも　まだまだ　これからですよ
But there is still much work to do.
We are approaching a time when the world cannot recover from the illness inflicted upon it.
世界は病に侵されて
取り返しのつかないところまで　きている
"Global Warming"
"Ozone Layer"
"Declining Birthrate"
Don't you feel it?
感じてるでしょう？　審判がやって来る　２０１２年
"Sexless"
"Earthquakes"
The time of judgment is coming. 2012.
"Natural Disasters"
"Abnormal Weather"
See that?
あれ見て
To prepare for the upcoming calamity,
we have prepared our "Ark of Salvation."
来るべき　大災厄に備えて
わたしたちは　救済の箱舟を用意しました
動物のつがいを　１組ずつ入れ
We'll put a pair of each animal inside it and one pair of man and woman.
そこに人間の男女１組も　乗り込みます
いうならば　ノアの箱舟です
It's basically Noah's Ark.
２人は　あの飛行船に乗り　大災厄を生き延びる
Two people will board that flying ship and will live on through the catastrophe.
そして地上が滅びた後　再び　現世に降りたら
Then, after the destruction is complete,
they will once again set foot on this earth and create a new world.
新しい世界を創造するのです
It's too bad the world can't go on like it is now.
このまま　世界が続くわけがない　残念だけど
わたしは　いつも悩んでる
But I always worry...
すると　誰かが尋ねる
Then, someone asks:
「最後の審判が来るので　悩んでるんですか？」
"Are you worried about the final judgment that's coming?"
"No, that's not it," I reply.
「いやっ　違うんです！」と　わたしは答える
"Even though the situation will be so hopeless,
「これだけ絶望的な状況に　なってるのに
まだ　考えを改めない者たちが　多いことに
what really causes me despair is the number of people
that do not change to a new way of thinking."
絶望しているのです」と
Right now, we only have a small, insignificant amount of power.
今や　われわれの微々たる力では
どうにもならない現状にきてる
しかし　努力は最後まで　続けなければいけません
However, we must continue our efforts until the very end.
願いが届かぬとも　最後まで頑張れた者は
The souls of those who struggle to the end without their wishes fulfilled
必ずや　魂の古里　プレアデスへと帰還できます
will quickly return home to the Pleiades.
After our bodies are destroyed,
肉体が滅んだ後
our free souls will be reborn as new life-forms and ascend to a new, higher stage.
自由意思の生命体として　生まれ変わり
今より高いステージへと　アセンションできるのです
There will be no need to worry about this troubling human life!
もう煩わしい人間関係などに　悩む必要はありません
Let's do it!
頑張りましょう！
Thank you for your support.
ご唱和ありがとう
Next, let me introduce my daughter.
えー　続いて　わが娘を紹介します
That's it?
そんだけ？
"Become a person"
Everyone, it seems you haven't opened your hearts yet.
みんな！　まだ　心　開いてないよね
心の底から思ってることを　吐き出して
ぶつけ合って　魂の交歓しないと
You can't continue to the next stage
unless you spill out everything from the bottom of your heart and confront your soul.
次のステージには進めないよ
Haven't you all just lived superficially?
みんな　うわべだけで　生きてこなかった？
もし　人生　うまくいってないとしたら
If your life hasn't gone so well, that's probably the reason.
原因は　そこにあると思うよ
All of my friends are successful.
僕の仲間は　みんな成功している
Why do you think that is?
なぜだと思う？
Because they show their souls.
魂をあらわにしてるからさ！
偉大な人物たちは　皆　このことを理解している
The truly great all understand this concept.
Blast out what you feel from the bottom of your heart!
心の底から思っていることを　吐き出して！
Everyone!
You're worthless!
お前は　駄目なやつだ！
食いながら　ダイエットの話　ばっかりして　豚！
You're always going on about a diet while you're stuffing your face!
You pig!
I've always thought your hairstyle was gross!
あなたの髪形　ずっと　キモいと思ってた！
You say you don't need a girlfriend, but you're just unpopular, aren't you?
「彼女いらない」とか言いながら　ホントは　モテないだけだろ！
I've had plastic surgery!
わたし　整形してるんです！
I have 5,000,000 in my bank account.
貯金が　５００万あります！
彼氏以外に　もう　２００人ぐらい　付き合ってました！
I've gone out with more than 200 people other than my boyfriend!
I wear a hairpiece!
かつらをかぶってます！
I can't love someone!
相手を愛せない！
親子映画なんて　ヘドが出るわ！
I throw up at family movies!
わたし　美人だと思ってる！
I think I'm beautiful!
I'm in crushing debt!
借金　踏み倒してやる！
あいつは　才能がない！
He's untalented!
便座　汚してやった！
I made a mess on the toilet seat!
金が目的
ダサいの！
I'm in it for the money!
Eww! Idiot!
Only the body!
Nobody ever loved me...
ちっとも愛されなかった
もういいんだ
It's okay now.
You understand each other.
君たちは　もう分かり合えたんだ
We'll all work together toward our happiness.
僕らは　もう同じ喜びを　共有するもの
魂の家族だ
We're family of the soul.
In this ugly world, here there is true love.
醜い世界の中で　ここには　本当の愛がある
You there.
君
Come to my room later.
後で　僕の部屋に来てください
It looks like you'll need some special guidance.
特別な指導が必要ですね
"Emotion" "Victim" "Devotion" "Friendship" "Pure" "Faith" "Service" "Effort" "Health" "Love"
"Hide Nothing" "Fraternity" "Bare" "Truth" "Reality"
It's coming!
来るぞ！
こっちに来る！？
It's coming this way!
壮絶な光景であった
It was quite the spectacle.
Apparently someone had hijacked the ark.
どうやら　何者かが　箱舟の強奪を企てたらしい
You're running, right?
逃げるんでしょ？　あっ…
I will accompany you.
お供しまっせ
Now, let's go.
さっ　早く！
And so we slipped into the dark forest to run away.
そうして　われわれは　暗い森を抜けて逃げた
Let's go to the next stop along the tracks.
また　線路をたどって　隣の駅に行きましょう
そこなら　きっと安全です
I'm sure that'll be safe.
There were even more people after us at the next station.
次の駅では　さらに追っ手が増えていた
何か　ほんわかでない連中も　交じっているようだった
And it seemed there were some
non-Honwaka people mixed in, too.
Hmm, Plan B.
うーんと　Ｂ作戦
Get in.
乗ってきな
But before that, one to warm you up, good customers?
その前に　一杯温まるかい？お得意さん
I didn't inquire about the details, but it seems this was the suggestion of one Master Higuchi.
詳しくは　聞けなかったが
樋口師匠という人物の　差し金らしかった
The Neko Ramen then was especially delicious,
その日の猫ラーメンは　格別おいしく
すすれば涙が出た
as I slurped it up, tears fell from my eyes.
それは　懐かしい　俗世の味
It was a worldly flavor I had missed so.
わたしは　心に決めた
I decided then and there
that even if the world were being destroyed tomorrow, I would take myself to Neko Ramen!
明日　世界が滅びようとも
猫ラーメンには　足を運ぼうと
Hey, please stop there!
はーい　ちょっと止まって
Not here!
いませーん！
We'll go down the canal to the Kamo River.
疎水を下って　鴨川まで行くんです
お前　何で　女装を？
Why are you in women's clothing?
Don't look at me with such a scary face!
いや～ん　そんな怖い顔で見ないで
おい　くっつくな！
Hey, get off me!
だって　寂しいんだもの
But I'm lonely and the river breeze is chilly...
川風が冷たいの
この寂しがり屋さんが！
You lonely bastard.
Ozu, what in the world have you done?
小津　お前は　いったい　何をしでかしたのだ！
着きましたね
We've arrived.
ここから　あなたは下宿の方へ
僕には　まだ　やぼ用がありますんで！
You head to the boarding house.
I still have some minor business to take care of!
明石です
It's Akashi. I've brought a Castella from the Master.
師匠から　カステラの差し入れ　持ってきました
どうぞ
Here.
The Master is here as well.
師匠も来てます
It seems things are over. It's okay now.
どうにか　決着はついたよ
もう大丈夫だ
小津の　これまでの悪事が　一気にバレたのだ
All Ozu's evil deeds until now have all been exposed,
失脚したついでに　賀茂大橋から飛び降りて
足の骨を折ったよ
and as a consequence he was thrown off the Kamo-oohashi and broke his leg.
He sure is one incorrigible fool.
あいつは　救い難いアホだな
あいつは　いったい　何者なんでしょうか？
What exactly is he?
Indeed. He's a slippery one to pin down.
そうさねぇ
捉えどころのない男だからな
But he said that he'd cover for you, come what may.
しかし　貴君のことも　「身をていしてかばう」と
勇ましいことを言っていたよ
This is your book, yes?
これは君の本だろう
I've finished reading it.
読み終わったんだ
And this seems to be yours as well.
これも君のらしい
わたしが知らずに使っていた
I used it unknowingly.
That's a book I bought at a used book fair.
これは　わたしが　古本市で買った　本である
I thought Ozu had borrowed it and
never returned it, but I guess this Master read it?
小津に貸して　戻ってこないままであったが
あの師匠と呼ばれる人物が　読んでいたのか
But it's been more than a year since then...
しかし　もう　かれこれ　１年以上前の話だ
Please use this!
これ　お使いください
I'll be in trouble if there are fewer bees.
ミツバチが減ると困ります　ガが増えてしまいますから
Because there'll be an increase in moths.
Clear-headed, in the engineering department, and smart enough to design airplanes,
頭脳明晰
工学部で　人力飛行機の設計までこなす
怖いもの知らずの明石さんだが
Akashi-san seemed to have no fear, except when it came to moths.
ガだけは苦手なようで
なくした　「もちぐま」を　捜していると言っていた
She told me she was looking for her lost Mochiguman.
好機は　目の前に　ぶら下がってございます
This opportunity is dangling right in front of your eyes.
I don't believe it! I don't!
信じないったら　信じない！
わたしは　オカルトなんて　信じない！
I don't believe in this crazy stuff!
Because it'd be really scary if it were true.
だって　ホントだったら　怖いではないか
How did something like this happen?
なぜ　こんなありさまに　なってしまったのか
光源氏も　かくやと思われた　愛らしき赤子時代より
Greater than the love Hikaru Genji felt for his infant daughter Kaguya,
こんな恐ろしい思いを　したことはなかった
I felt fear the likes of which I'd never felt before.
あのまま　ほんわかに　なじんでいれば
At this rate, would I not have been happier staying with Honwaka?
それはそれで　幸せだったのではないか
いや　わたしは　２年の歳月を棒に振ったのだ
No, I have thrown away these past two years.
この事実に対して　断固として　目をつぶってはならぬ！
I must face this reality head on, with conviction!
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!